<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Elmer Press</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Clinical Medicine Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1918-3003</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1918-3011</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elmer Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4021/jocmr1685w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation in Diffuse Alveolar Hemorrhage Secondary to Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Claudio</surname><given-names>Christine Pacheco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aa">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Charbonney</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Ab">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>Madeleine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Ac">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kolan</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Ac">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laskine</surname><given-names>Mikhael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Ac">c</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CORd">d</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aa"><label>a</label>Centre Hospitalier de l&#8217;Universite de Montreal, Montreal, Canada</aff><aff id="Ab"><label>b</label>Hopital de Trois-Rivieres and Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal, Montreal, Canada</aff><aff id="Ac"><label>c</label>Department of Medicine, Hopital Hotel-Dieu, CRCHUM, Montreal, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CORd"><label>d</label>Corresponding author: Mikhael Laskine, Department of Medicine, Hopital Hotel-Dieu, Centre Hospitalier de l&#8217;Universite de Montreal, 3840 St-Urbain Street, Door 4-411, Montreal, Quebec H2W 1T8, Canada.  Email: <email> mikhael.laskine.chum@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>04</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>02</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2014, Claudio et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Diffuse alveolar hemorrhage (DAH) is a rare and potentially deadly complication of systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE). We report two adult cases where extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) was used as rescue therapy for severe respiratory failure in this setting. We discuss the risk related to coagulation disturbance and the need for the circuit anticoagulation in this particular setting. We also briefly discuss the clinical problem of lack of knowledge on the bioavailability of the immunosuppressive treatment with the use of ECMO. We think that ECMO should be used as rescue therapy in patients with DAH caused by SLE, but strategies for anticoagulation require further precision.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation</kwd><kwd>Diffuse alveolar hemorrhage</kwd><kwd>Systemic lupus erythematosus</kwd><kwd>Systemic anticoagulation</kwd><kwd>Continuous veno-venous hemodialysis</kwd><kwd>Bioavailability</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Given the need of anticoagulation to prevent the formation of thrombus in the circuit, difficulties can be encountered in case of DAH, where preventing both thrombotic and hemorrhagic complications associated with ECMO becomes a challenge. In addition, patients diagnosed with DAH secondary to systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and other auto-immune diseases often present both an inflammatory state in addition to thrombocytopenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>] and platelet dysfunction.</p><p>The use of ECMO as rescue therapy for refractory hypoxemia secondary to DAH caused by SLE has been reported in the pediatric population. Outcomes in one case series appear favorable despite the added risk of bleeding conferred by this type of hemodynamic support [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>].</p><p>Its use in this particular clinical circumstance has only previously been described in one adult patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Case Report</title><p>Initial work-up demonstrated diffuse bilateral alveolar infiltrates on chest X-ray, and no evidence of any acute abdominal process on abdomen CT. Bronchoscopy was performed and confirmed alveolar hemorrhage. Blood cultures were positive for Klebsiella pneumonaie, and broad-spectrum antibiotic coverage was initiated.</p><p>The patient was then admitted to ICU for sepsis and hypoxemic respiratory insufficiency requiring mechanical ventilation in the setting of SLE flare-up. Over the next 24 h, the patient remained significantly hypoxemic despite conventional mechanical ventilation at maximal settings in pressure-controlled mode, with peak airway pressures of 50 cmH2O, positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) of 16 cmH2O, at a rate of 12 breaths/min with a FiO2 of 1.0. Despite various attempts to improve the oxygenation, her clinical deterioration required an alternate mode of oxygenation as rescue therapy.</p><p>Veno-venous ECMO was therefore initiated via, as usual in our institution, a heparin-coated 27 French double lumen AvalonTM cannula placed in the right jugular vein. For the first 24 h, we used the trillium-coated Affinity NT filter (Medtronic&#174;), then we changed it to heparin-coated Quadrox D filter (Maquet&#174;) for the sake of effectiveness and long-term use. Systemic anticoagulation was not initiated because of the DAH. Initial output was 3.4 L/min and saturation measured on pulse oximetry rose quickly to over 94%. Pulse corticosteroids and intravenous cyclophosphamide were also initiated.</p><p>The patient recovered and was weaned off mechanical ventilation after 10 days. Creatinine returned to baseline. The patient was discharged from hospital on oral prednisone (60 mg daily) and intravenous cyclophosphamide. He was stable and free of neurologic sequelae at his last follow-up appointment 1 year later (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Recruitment Strategies Identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>] </title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>This is the footnotes of this table.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>We report two cases of the use of ECMO in the setting of DAH secondary to SLE disease flare-up in adult population.</p><p>ECMO is generally used as rescue or bridge therapy, for cases where conventional ventilation and hemodynamic support measures have failed to improve the patient&#8217;s clinical condition. General indications for the use of ECMO are cardiac pump failure, secondary to cardiotomy or inability to wean cardiopulmonary bypass follow heart surgery, or heart failure, and respiratory insufficiency, more commonly secondary to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>], notably in the context of H1N1 epidemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>], pneumonia or graft dysfunction following lung transplant.</p><p>Formal indications for ECMO are severe hypoxemia with a PaO2/FiO2 of &lt; 100 mmHg despite optimal ventilator settings or an alveolar arterial gradient of more than 600 mmHg in the absence of cardiogenic pulmonary edema or hypercapnia with a pH of less than 7.20 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>]. ECMO is contraindicated in cases of irreversible respiratory or cardiac disease, in patients over the age of 65 years old, or in patients who have been mechanically ventilated for over 5 days.</p><p>Complications of ECMO include hemorrhage, thromboembolism, local infection and, less commonly, technical problems related to cannulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>].</p><p>Patients with DAH are particularly vulnerable to increased bleeding risk. In one case series of pediatric patients with DAH secondary to multiple baseline pathologies, patients were anticoagulated, albeit at slight lower clotting time levels, and did not have more hemorrhagic complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. In the adult population, the initiation of ECMO without anticoagulation has been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]. The subsequent initiation of heparin caused profuse bleeding which was difficult to control, and required the use of aminocaproic acid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]. In the case of SLE-induced DAH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>], systemic anticoagulation was initiated upon the installation of ECMO. No notable hemorrhagic complications were reported. Our first case illustrates how the use of heparin, albeit only to rinse the CVVH circuit, led to a significant increase in alveolar hemorrhage. It is the first case in the literature to our knowledge where the use of anticoagulation has aggravated DAH significantly. There were no thrombotic complications related to ECMO in this patient where heparin was not used. In our second patient, a thrombus did form in the circuit; however, there were no associated consequences.</p><p>Alternative measures to systemic anticoagulation in order to decrease the risk of clot formation in extracorporeal circuits exist. The use of regional citrate anticoagulation in critically ill patients at increased risk for bleeding requiring CVVH is a recognized alternative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]. This alternative to anticoagulation with an ECMO circuit has preliminarily been explored in animal studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] where no clot formation was noted in circuits after 24 h, but further studies are required in human subjects. Using anticoagulation with lower standard clotting time parameters in the pediatric population, as proposed by Kolovos et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>], should equally be considered in adult patients with DAH. The use of ECMO without anticoagulation has also been described in trauma patients. Muellenbach et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>] reported the prolonged use of ECMO without heparin as rescue therapy for ARDS in three patients with multiple injuries including traumatic brain injury, a contraindication to systemic anticoagulation. One of the three patients was diagnosed with thromboembolic disease in the inferior vena cava, appreciated on follow-up imaging after the discontinuation of ECMO and eventually required anticoagulation.</p><p>Another aspect of these two cases is the bioavailability of the immunosuppressive treatment with the use of ECMO as a supportive therapy. Indeed mainstay treatment of SLE flare-up with or without DAH consists of pulse IV corticosteroids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>] with the addition of immunosuppressive agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>], notably cyclophosphamide, which appears to confer a better prognosis in a case-series of patients with SLE-induced DAH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. Unfortunately little is known about the bioavailability of the cyclophosphamide or other immunosuppressive agent in the setting of ECMO and whether dose adjustment is necessary.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="s4"><title>Grant Support</title><p>No grant support.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nossent</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaak</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><article-title>Prevalence and significance of haematological abnormalities in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title><source>Q J Med</source><year>1991</year><volume>80</volume><issue>291</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1946940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kolovos</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuerer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moler</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bratton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaniker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Custer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Extracorporal life support for pulmonary hemorrhage in children: a case series</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003246-200203000-00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11990918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipchik</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><article-title>Systemic lupus-induced diffuse alveolar hemorrhage treated with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation: a case report and review of the literature</article-title><source>J Intensive Care Med</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885066612464335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23753220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mugford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiruvoipati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thalanany</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibbert</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Efficacy and economic assessment of conventional ventilatory support versus extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe adult respiratory failure (CESAR): a multicentre randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2009</year><volume>374</volume><issue>9698</issue><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61069-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19762075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beca</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellomo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for 2009 influenza A(H1N1) acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2009</year><volume>302</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>1888</fpage><lpage>1895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2009.1535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19822628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holena</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McCunn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>A review of the fundamental principles and evidence base in the use of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) in critically ill adult patients</article-title><source>J Intensive Care Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885066610384061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21262750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Highland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Use of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation in a patient with diffuse alveolar hemorrhage</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.126.1.305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15249477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalb</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Slowinski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindgen-Milles</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Regional citrate anticoagulation for high volume continuous venovenous hemodialysis in surgical patients with high bleeding risk</article-title><source>Ther Apher Dial</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-9987.2012.01101.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23551677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pinnick</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegmann</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Diederich</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>Regional citrate anticoagulation for hemodialysis in the patient at high risk for bleeding</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1983</year><volume>308</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM198302033080506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6848936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jr</surname><given-names/></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwischenberger</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><article-title>Percutaneous venovenous CO2 removal with regional anticoagulation in an ovine model</article-title><source>ASAIO J</source><year>2006</year><volume>52</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.mat.0000227743.07743.5d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16883129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muellenbach</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kredel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunze</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuestermann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Prolonged heparin-free extracorporeal membrane oxygenation in multiple injured acute respiratory distress syndrome patients with traumatic brain injury</article-title><source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1444</fpage><lpage>1447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22673280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jr</surname><given-names/></name><name><surname>Freundlich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Callegari</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><article-title>Pulmonary alveolar hemorrhage in systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title><source>Semin Arthritis Rheum</source><year>1993</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0049-0172(05)80022-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santos-Ocampo</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fessler</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><article-title>Alveolar hemorrhage in systemic lupus erythematosus: presentation and management</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2000</year><volume>118</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.118.4.1083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martinez-Martinez</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Abud-Mendoza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Predictors of mortality in diffuse alveolar haemorrhage associated with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title><source>Lupus</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0961203310392430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21558137</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>